William Kienbusch Letters to Francis and Sydney Hamabe
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
William Kienbusch letters to Francis and Sydney Hamabe
1958-1977
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Kienbusch, William
0.2 linear feet
The William Kienbusch letters to Francis and Sydney Hamabe measure 0.2 linear feet and date from 1958 to 1977. Found in this collection are 93 letters and postcards in which Kienbusch discusses his work as a landscape painter and art instructor in New York and Maine, family business, activities with the Hamabes, their mutual friends, and other artists. Included as letter attachments are newspaper clippings and three catalogs for Kienbusch exhibitions at Kraushaar Gallery from 1959, 1969, and 1975.
Provenance
The letters were donated in 1984 by Francis Hamabe.
Related Material
Also found in the Archives of American Art are the William Kienbusch papers, 1915-2001; the Walter Maitland correspondence with and about William Kienbusch, 1969-1981; the Thomas Barrett and Leni Mancuso papers relating to William Kienbusch, 1950-1980; and an oral history interview with William Kienbusch conducted by Forrest Selvig, November 1-7, 1968.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on 35 mm microfilm reel 3118 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
William Kienbusch (1914-1980) was a painter and art instructor in New York, NY, and Cranberry Island, Maine. Kienbusch befriended Rockport, Maine artist Francis Hamabe (1917-2002) and his wife Sydney (1917-1978). Hamabe was the co-founder of the Maine Coast Artists Association.
Scope and Content Note
The William Kienbusch letters to Francis and Sydney Hamabe measure 0.2 linear feet and date from 1958 to 1977. Found in this collection are 93 letters and postcards in which Kienbusch discusses his work as a landscape painter and art instructor in New York and Maine, family business, activities with the Hamabes, their mutual friends, and other artists. Included as letter attachments are newspaper clippings and three catalogs for Kienbusch exhibitions at Kraushaar Gallery from 1959, 1969, and 1975.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as one series:
Series 1: William Kienbusch Letters to Francis and Sydney Hamabe, 1958-1977 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Hamabe, Sydney, 1918-; Hamabe, Francis, 1917-; Kraushaar Galleries
Subjects-Topical:
Art teachers--Maine; Art teachers--New York (State)--New York; Landscape painters--Maine; Landscape painters--New York (State)--New York
Types of Materials:
Postcards
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- William Kienbusch Letters to Francis and Sydney Hamabe, 1958-1977, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
  - Letters, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)